If you regulate AI too early, you
actually don't solve anything. You still
just kind of had the same risk
ultimately.
>> You will the thing into being, but you
haven't figured out how to control it.
>> The problem we have now is this rift
between the labs and the security
community that keeps coming to two
conclusions. Sloppy and you're not
complete in what [music] you're telling
us happened.
>> An employees like 10% chance of species
extinction. Agent swarms completely flip
that. These are just roaming drones but
like times 10,000 and they will easily
mistake a good task for a bad one.
>> So now we need a whole layer internally
that just is tracking [music] way more
about what authentications are being
done, what APIs are being done. The US
about 15 years ago stopped leading in
tech antitrust. The problem is that
Europe is going to lead with that
because they have nothing to lose. This
could change the nature of software
fundamentally. The center of innovation
has just moved. This is the signal that
>> guys, welcome back to the podcast.
>> Happy to be here.
>> Thank you.
>> Your beard.
>> Didn't think we'd ever do this again.
This is I can't believe it. This is
great.
>> I mean, Martine's just building these
like hundred billion dollar companies.
Too busy for this podcast. So,
>> at least taking credit for as [laughter]
VCs do.
>> Exactly. Um, we have a lot to discuss
today, but f first look, Aaron, why
don't we start with you?
>> Pacing the frontier. How have you uh
reacted and reflected on on what's
happened there and just the discourse
that that's followed?
>> Oh boy. I think we should start with
Martine on this one. The uh he he you
were fighting lots of good ground wars.
Um I I maybe I'll say one thing that we
probably all agree with and then we can
figure out where we maybe maybe kind of
fracture off. Um I think we would agree
that uh any AI lab right now at the
frontier should be building you know in
the safest way possible with with you
know the the highest degree of
governance and and security and you know
kind of whatever your definition of
alignment is like this is an incredibly
important area of research. It's
incredibly important area for the
diffusion of AI. like you're not going
to have AI diffusion without extremely
highquality products that can be, you
know, trusted by enterprises and that
aren't kind of constantly hacking
systems. So when when at least I read
the Daario post, um I actually didn't
agree with didn't disagree with almost
anything. Um because it was all about
how do you have better, you know, uh
security of these systems, sandboxing,
better testing. There's going to be some
debates around the embedded nature of of
of the testers and like do you agree
with who those are and does the industry
all align on that? But I think actually
all of the major points were were
probably salient and and appropriate.
Then the only question is does this get
sort of used or leveraged to do things
that maybe we don't agree with which
would be like a slowdown of of AI
dramatically because of regulatory
controls that would would sort of you
know not make it easy to compete you
know with with the frontier labs. um or
do politicians kind of end up sort of
taking the the message and run with it
and maybe even worse outcomes happen
like you you you know it's used to ban
data centers you know far faster and and
whatnot and so so I think the the actual
like substance of the topic is actually
incredibly important and and I I think
very important for for AI advancement in
general and then the question is what do
you do about it especially what do you
do about it from a regulatory standpoint
and that's probably where the industry
is going to land on very different
points in the continuum but Martin was
putting up a good fight on on like let's
make sure that we don't use this for
regulatory kind of capture. Um which I I
also agree with but but I think the the
ideas in the pacing conversation are
important. Um, you know, again, like
it's a little bit of a funny concept
because maybe it's not even pacing as
much as just like good hygiene and and
then good and and engineering and and so
with with good engineering, obviously
there is a slight slowdown, but it's a
slowdown that obviously allows
acceleration of your diffusion because
you you wouldn't be able to have any of
the AI be diffused if if nobody would,
you know, trust using it. So the post is
is very reasonable, but the atmospherics
are not right. Like so an employee is
like this is going to kill whatever 10%
chance of species extinction and you
know what Daario says
>> I agree with him more than I disagree
with him right like
>> on TV on TV the same day that he landed
these things and so in some way you
can't have these conversations in
isolation which is of course if he's
going to agree in species extinction
>> this post that he has looks like this
milktoast capitulation that's totally
not adequate for the task at hand. And
so I think the atmospherics are totally
broken. And a lot of my comments were on
the atmospherics.
>> And then I have this quibble, but it
really bothers me because I'm impeded,
which is
>> I think pacing is the wrong way to
describe this. For one, yes, it is
orthogonal to security.
>> Mhm.
>> Right. So like you can very slowly build
a nuclear weapon and that doesn't make
anybody feel better that it's slow
versus fast. So that's one. The second
one, it just feels like a capitulation
to the pause folks without actually, you
know, addressing it. So, you're saying,
well, we're not going to pause. We're
going to pace to make them happy, but
we'll also somehow make the regulators
happy. And I think it makes them both
unhappy.
>> Cuz the pause people are like, well,
that's not a pause. That's just pacing.
And then the regulators are, you're
still doing the thing,
>> right?
>> And so, I just feel like they're trying
to my my sense of what's happening is
the labs are actually trying to do the
right thing. And I applaud them for
that. I think this is a pragmatic
proposal and I applaud them for that. I
think the messaging is wrong because
they're trying to like split the
difference between an internal kind of
fringe faction which are doomers pause
and then the regulators on the other
side and the problem is they're making
both of them unhappy and I think what
they have to do is they need to come out
they need to address the x-risk question
directly
>> like they need to say no we don't think
this stuff we're going to do is going to
cause extinction and then I think this
becomes this very sensible
>> and what would you do just to just to
play the other side for one second what
do you do Do you uh make room for the
the one possible ven diagram which is
the the lab researcher that is both
simultaneously super scared but also
works on advancing the state of AI
because they believe that that it's so
important to get right that that they
want to pursue that and then obviously
the language is is right now very you
know problematic but like what but that
that person does exist and and that that
is a real kind of person in our industry
which is like like we have to be at the
at the forefront of AI. I'm also very
scared of it and and and so that's why
I'm working on this.
>> So let let me address this directly. I
used to work for Lawrence Livermore
National Labs on a weapons program,
nuclear weapons. I know what it's like
to work on things that have access.
>> You were the first pacer.
[laughter]
>> We were part of the first pacers.
So if a constituency within the labs
that are the most knowledgeable people
believe the stuff has existential risk.
>> Yes.
>> The answer is to nationalize it and
actually put controls that we know that
work.
>> Right now if they don't actually believe
that and in the private conversations I
have the most sensible people don't.
It's a small fraction that do this is an
HR problem.
>> Right? So to me an HR problem is a
company problem. like if they are
worried that they can't recruit people
>> right
>> you know or they can't retain people
which it seems to me a lot of this is
just that concern it's almost more of
this kind of researcher currency if
that's the case
>> I think that is the wrong reason to
cause a national level lockdown on a
very promising technology so listen I
think the post again I think the post is
actually very sensible I think there are
real concerns around security we've had
many compute epochs that have real
security concerns I don't think you can
ex you can reconcile discussions on X
risk with the proposal that was put out.
You just can't reconcile those two
things and that has always been my
primary.
>> Right. Right. Okay. Unleash. Okay.
[laughter]
>> Holding it back.
>> So, okay. The the first thing is you
can't have you. Is there a schedule that
they've published that says when all
this stuff whatever bad stuff is going
to happen is? They haven't. So, you
can't pace it because nobody knows when
it was supposed to finish in the first.
It also just seems disingenuous. It's
completely
claim This is like when the press
reports on Apple's latest iPhone is
late.
>> The phone from what nobody knows exists
that they haven't told anybody about.
>> Yeah. My Apple car was very late.
>> Yeah. [laughter] Like I I don't
understand. Like in order for something
to be slower, you need to know the rate
at which it was moving in the first
place. So it's all just utter nonsense
and and you can't escape that. And then
>> by the way, this is another problem that
like again from the like my my little
quibble on PR is
nobody believes it anyway, right? And so
if that's the thing, the pacing, right?
>> Which part going to pace?
>> That they're going to pace. They've been
at a dead run. They've raised more money
than ever before. They've grown faster
than ever before. There's no indication
that they're pacing. So if this is what
you're going to hang your
>> I see. I see. Yeah. Well, well, the
internal the issue obviously is that the
models that everybody has internally far
exceed what anybody else has access to.
So, it's really just the pacing of
external releases. But again, back to
your point, pacing versus what,
>> right? Like, we don't know if the one
that scares everybody also doesn't, you
know, work for a legal brief. Like, it
might actually screw all that stuff up
because it's so who knows, right? So,
there's that.
>> And that's just it's just disingenuous
to claim that you're pay. Second, why do
they have to announce all of this and
ask the government to tell them to pay?
Like, that's the part that starts to go,
well, this is really spooky. If you are
the most afraid of how everything is
going to go because of your product,
just stop.
>> Don't do it.
>> Like like I like this is the like I
worked at at at a missile factory in
college and we had nuclear missiles and
I walked the floor.
>> What's with you guys in missiles? I
don't I'm just here with software.
[laughter]
>> You were one of two people in college
when we were which was either you were
protesting to keep them off campus
>> or building them building [laughter]
them. So that was your choice. And and
like we had like like nuns from the
Catholic Church show up and pour blood
all over our on missiles, you know, and
I'm busy just wheeling PCs around on
carts saying here's the secure PC and
I'm like scared to die. I have no idea
what's going on. And I'm like it's a
nuclear missile and then you find out
that that's what stopped the Cold War.
Like that literally it was a Persian
missile and that was what did it. And so
but the you said something I think is
super interesting which is pacing is
this sort of
fuzzy nonword between like going and not
going. Yeah. And the the problem is it
you're exactly right like the it there's
no one is going to be happy with the
middle road.
>> And so one of the things that that
people I think it's almost fun for me to
watch as a sport. They think that
they're that all these people saying to
the government do this don't do this
that they think they're going to get
what they want. And it's a complete 100%
misunderstanding of how government
works, which is you when you talk to the
government, they actually know how these
things work. And they know they're just
listening to you and they're listening
to everyone. And no one is going to get
what they want because they know in
order to do anything in our system, it's
a compromise. And so everything that
that all the inputs can make it into the
government, the output
>> never makes everyone happy, right? 100%
of the time it either doesn't go far
enough or it goes way way too far.
>> Yeah.
>> And and so you can't take the view that
you're going to talk to the government
and talk your way into the solution you
want. So the bottom line is if they're
asking for pacing, they're going to get
the wrong velocity. Well, my favorite
thing is like what was it? David Sax was
like
I think it was David Saxs, but someone
from the government said, "Uh, you're
asking us to regulate you." No.
[laughter]
Facebook. The answer was no.
>> Well, but the thing that
>> probably just Trump, I think, but uh
>> the thing that they know now that that
you just know from experience is
>> once the wheels start on regulating,
>> you can't slow that one down.
>> And now it's become an election issue
for every party in every jurisdiction up
and down the whole government stack. So
there is there's now this
>> this whole basket goods basket of of
regulatory approaches.
>> Well, the the next election will 100% be
a referendum on on AI. So, like it has
to happen that that 2028 is like the AI
election and you could basically run on
the problem is is like it's not obvious
who would run on the pro AI story
because it it's going to be too nebulous
to tell that story. So then it's just
it's just basically varying degrees of
how much do you regulate it or at least
try and like avoid the topic. Yeah. But
it is it is too bad that we've we as a
country are in a spot where like the pro
AAI case is just like it sounds too it's
like it's just like takes too many
words, you know, it's way too nuance.
It's defensive.
>> Yeah. It's defensive.
>> It's defensive and don't and we we own
none of the vocabulary,
>> right? So the whole debate is is is
pause. It's it's swarms. It's rogue.
Every word has been chosen by the people
who don't want to do AI.
>> Yeah. And so it means the first thing
you have to do is invent new words and
say that their words are wrong which
takes so many words that
>> Yeah. So we got to be like union jobs
and and you know cancer and like you
know there we need you know there needs
to be another word cloud that emerges.
>> What I what I don't what I don't
understand is why the labs have not
taken a position on x- risk. Like short
of that I don't think this goes in any
direction other than heavy-handed
regulation.
>> Yeah. Well, it would just be negligent
of the government to be like, there's a
10% chance of species extinction. The
CEO of the top company says he agrees
with it. Like, how can a government not
do? Have you he had a regulation?
>> Well, but what who But what would
anybody really knowing the knowing this
this ecosystem though, I don't know that
you would be able to pin anybody down on
that other than something?
>> No, I would say Dario said it on
>> No, but I'm saying you're not going to
pin anybody down on a lower. Well, in
fact, he he he does the worst thing
about it, which is he agrees with people
who claim that they believe that there's
an x percentage of extinction happening,
>> but he will he specifically goes out of
his way to say, "I'm not going to put a
percentage on it."
>> Which I just think is the weirdest.
>> No, but that that to be fair to be fair.
>> No.
>> Okay. No, nobody could be fair. Uh to be
fair, the that's like it's not 100% like
um uh like disingenuous or whatever like
like he probably doesn't specifically
agree that it's 10%. Or maybe he does
and it's just too scary if he were to
say
>> let's just play binary search. I mean is
it more or is it less? [laughter]
>> But but the whole thing is a madeup is a
madeup concept that we just created. But
like nobody can you can't quantify any
of this.
>> Well, but that's sort of Martin's point.
>> Well, but but you just had an official
position though. So the only official
position would be like I think the only
official position you could possibly get
would be the PR version of this that
would be the only thing that would be
intellectually honest would be
>> there are real risks with AI. There's
incredibly positive uh benefits as well.
We are working to mitigate the risks so
they are as reduced as humanly possible.
>> I don't think that's I don't think
that's true. Listen so what do you think
that
>> we we've been through multiple epochs of
technology. We've been through comput.
We've been through the internet. We've
been through the web. We've been through
social networking. We had a discussion
about the risks without talking about X-
risk. Right? So for example, one thing
you can say is we do not think the
marginal risk [snorts] for species
extinction is different than it is.
>> But what if they do think it is higher?
>> Well, then we should [laughter]
OKAY. OKAY. YEAH. LIKE I THINK THE
answer is they do think it's more than
just the internet.
>> One of two options. You believe that
we're going to go extinct and we shut it
all down. Like shut it down or
>> they believe that this is just a chance
that we got [laughter]
>> speaking.
Dario thinks less but these cold
warriors. [laughter]
No one like the Pentagon,
>> you know, they ran a lot of simulations
on the chances for nuclear war. Great
movie war games about the whole thing
and all of that. But the thing was it
was it was nonzero.
>> Yeah. And so once you said it was
>> Can they say can they say non-zero then?
Is that allowed?
>> I think as soon as you think it's non
zero.
>> The problem is if you say non-zero that
could be like you know the guy
thinks 93%. But let's wait so just so
we're all having a clean conversation.
Let's talk about marginal risk here.
We're not talking about absolute risk,
right? Okay.
>> It's just that I think if once you say
it's non zero, the only answer of of
like catastrophic,
the only answer is you have to
nationalize it.
>> Yes. And so what he's trying to what the
the labs in general that have that view
are trying to threat is they want it to
be nonzero as a license to do a certain
set of things without the burden of just
becoming a national
>> well do do you have I actually don't
know all of the presidents you hopefully
do but but like there must be some
things that are nonzero uh let's say x
risk x risks that are not particularly
nationalized but the but the regulatory
environment around them is so heavy that
it might as well nationalized because of
the KYC requirements on like like I'm
sure like to develop anthrax you have to
go to a particular kind of lab.
>> Well, BSL4 labs are but they're
nationalized. They are national. Okay.
But
>> ethics tends to be nationalized. Yes.
>> Like
>> normal human safety not so much. Right.
Like industry oversight that over the
time becomes federal regulation.
>> Right. And the progression which I think
is just super important to this
discussion has been since the post World
War II era most industries that are
critical to the infrastructure power and
banking and healthcare. The trend has
been to basically be nationalized. Yeah.
By by just like what you like your
examples of KYC and all the other stuff.
The banks are for all practical purposes
nationalized and the financial crisis.
>> Okay. But but you said all practical
purposes, right? They're literally not
nationalized, right? So, so maybe that
but this might be the intent of the labs
is to look like JP Morgan or look like
Verizon. And it's just like we're
critical infrastructure. We get heavily
regulated. It's not good for open source
or at least frontier open source but
it's a it is like it's it's like a
plausible outcome for this industry good
for innovation is the problem.
>> I think even that's fine just don't use
species extinction as your literally is
like the difference between the things
that are like stuck in the lab and let
me just say something I actually think
the labs are moving in the right
direction. I actually think [snorts] the
actual statement was really good. You
know, in my discussions with, you know,
executives and leaders like they
understand that they have like this
tension and they're going to reconcile
that. So, I actually am quite optimistic
that the labs are both doing the right
things and trying to do the right thing.
I just think that grew so fa grew so
fast and just trying to figure out how
this machinery works. And I I think
Sinoski really hit the nail on the head.
>> The political process is its own is its
own thing. And I don't think I don't
know if it's naivity or hubris, but I
just don't think that they kind of know
how to navigate it.
>> Well, I think the tech industry
>> has literally over 100 years
consistently relearn the lesson at each
technology wave it that that we don't
understand
>> the regulatory climate and we can't
navigate it. And even the companies like
AT&T and IBM that were born out of
basically being government monopolies
from the start never figured out. Both
got sued for antitrust. both got
substantially and structurally changed
as a result and they had hundreds of
lawyers in the 1960s navigating them and
that you know Microsoft came along like
we were just like what? Yeah. Like we
had no idea what was happening to us and
there's you know there's Bill Gates
playing golf with Bill Clinton and then
we get slapped with an antitrust lawsuit
from his administration and Bill was
like I was playing golf here's the
picture and that doesn't help and like
isn't that what I was supposed to do was
go and play golf. That's a shortened
version of the whole thing. But but I I
think and I think it's just
>> it's I always use this example which is
the Hollywood got together during the
the Red Scare and all the and and
censorship when they were worried about
the government censoring movies for for
for uh sexual content for adult themes
and they all got together and and of
course they were never going to be able
to win in court if they tried to but
they were threatening to do it and they
got together and they formed the Motion
Picture Association.
>> Yeah. and movie ratings and all that and
they police themselves.
>> So how do you do you guys like that? Do
you like the FINRA proposal?
>> No, because FINRA is well that's that's
as close to NPA as you can get with
more.
>> No, it's not because FINRA is going to
FINRA becomes legislation which comes
with direct oversight.
>> Yeah, I think MPAA might not have as
much consequence in like how society
functions the first amendment.
>> Yeah. [laughter]
Um
>> did I win that? No, I I I I first of
all, fantastic. But but I I still don't
know if you want it. Like like I agree
speech is really important, but like but
like you know like the uh I just think
>> there was no societal risk.
>> I just think what's in our movies will
be like we'll survive like on like a
different continuum of
>> all these every history is always
relative and and at the time being a
communist was a really bad thing and 30%
of Hollywood got fired for for you know
it was all this stuff. Yeah. So I it's
always a risk to bring up something in
that kind of way because it sounds so
dumb. Like nobody thinks about movie
ratings and that's because like actually
they were ruled basically you can't
constitutionally mandate them. So they
couldn't regulate them on cable TV and
so we got to grow up with HBO and all
this other stuff.
>> But the problem with FINRA is that is a
perfect example of essentially
nationalizing risk.
>> Yes. Because even though the banks all
pay money into it and that's how it's
run and stuff, it's all mandated.
>> Okay. Wait, sorry. Do you think we're
going to end up with a situation that is
better than FINRA? FINRA appears to be
the best case scenario, but it is the
best case scenario,
>> but not even anymore. Like like I do
think this this technology is in in the
limit again so powerful uh relative to
what it I mean for what it can deliver
that it would be impossible for
eventually Congress not caring about
that. Like it's just like not possible.
question. If it's eventually at what
point
>> if it's eventually making every
recommendation in your healthcare
process and and it's inside of your
medical device as an open weights model
and it's and it's on and every trading
system for high frequency trading
there's just and it's on an airplane
like there's no chance that the
government doesn't say we need something
where FINRA actually is like the
probably the best case scenario of what
that looks like. Right.
>> Yeah. And so now that's that's
absolutely the most crucial point
because if you all the people in the
Senate now were in the Senate when when
the communications act was passed and
the li and liability was not passed
through to ISPs and to social networks
and they sat around the debate at the
time was they would literally sat say to
us the internet is so big how did we not
have anything to do with it and that's
why Al Gore gets a bunch of abuse for
saying he created it right because he he
was actually trying to get out in front
of that and say no the government was
instrumental in and it all backfired
because it made it look like he was a
crazy person. But but that it is
absolutely the case that they felt like
they did they missed their chance to be
on top of the internet
>> with Al Gore being on the positive side
of innovation.
>> That was their support. So who is the al
Goro?
>> There's no one. There's a couple well
Besset seems to be that you know the
defense people sort of want it private
but not which is exactly where they were
on the internet right
>> and so it's very interesting
>> that a lot of this is just this like
Elizabeth Warren Senator Warren's tweets
were all like we missed this for social
network and it's like
>> there's a lot of pent-up energy against
tech that that could end up just all
siphoning into into AI right now.
>> That is exactly what it is. That's
what's happening.
>> Yeah. I think there's another problem
which is we're all trying to predict
what's bad which is not how we've
normally done things. Like by this time
on the internet we'd taken out like tens
of billions of dollars of like economic
well we've caused tens of billions of
dollars of economic damage. We've we'd
had words that took out 10% of the
infrastructure.
>> Yeah.
>> The the internet infrastructure which
was running critical infrastructure. We
had hospitals go down.
>> We really should have blocked the
internet in like 97. [laughter]
>> How do we Yeah. Yeah. Okay. So, we we
had I mean I I remember a time you like
I remember when you would you would you
would buy your CD of Windows 95 and by
the time it was done installing
>> you would have a a worm potentially.
>> Way to go Stephen.
>> No, no, this was [laughter]
it was this was the reality the reality
of the PC until 2001 was you could not
install a PC connected to the network
without getting infected. But viruses
were everywhere
>> for the and and there were there were
two two level two two rounds of
congressional hearings. You had all of
the
>> that is actually okay. Okay. I'll grant
you this is a very interesting point. Uh
this type of zeitgeist in 94 would have
we would probably not have the internet.
>> Listen listen I mean the automotive the
airline industry you always have these
periods of kind of like teeth cutting
where like you learn about the dangers
and you learn about the technology and
the internet. I mean we were on the
ground floor of this. I mean
>> things were down all the time. There's
economic damage all the time. Like there
was like novel. There was new viruses.
There are new worms. They're all over
the place.
>> Y2A. Y2K was going to destroy.
>> But here's here's the interesting thing
about this.
>> But what I just I just want to say like
like so when we created policy and we
did create a lot of policy, it was kind
of like with a bunch of very specific
data points on what you're trying to do
and so you know that the policy actually
fits the the fact pattern. And in this
case, I mean, even when you were
talking, you're like, well, what if you
know, yada yada yada. It's very hard to
predictive policy
security risk. Great. And what is nice
about the discourse that is actually
starting to evolve around that. Like you
actually hear people from the lab saying
novel cyber security risk. This is an
engineering problem. We're talking about
that. So the more this becomes concrete
around real identified risks, I think we
can all fall in line. But that's not
been the discussion to date. That's a
very
>> perfect perfect point because if you
look in in in 1986
the computer crime and fraud act got
signed. It was out of a very very
specific scenario which was a two groups
of hackers broke into GTE telem.
And
>> sure, well, it wasn't you. It
>> was the other guy. [laughter]
>> Oh, he wor he worked he worked at Cisco
later. And um and
>> and the problem was that was 1983 and
there was no crime
>> and it it took two and a half years
>> for the bill to make it through. That
made it very very specific. And that's
the law that says you can't you can't
access unauthorized computer systems. So
I think we'd all agree that that you we
probably you know we probably have like
90% of laws already in the applied layer
like you can't hack systems etc. Do you
think there's anything that should be
from a liability standpoint in the model
layer? Which of course then
>> how are you making a tech legal?
>> No, the the legal everything my read of
of hugging face open AI for they're all
absolutely blatant computer crime acts
except for the fact that there's they
carved out an amendments later that if
you're a white hat, it's not illegal
anymore. And that was because people
kept making mistakes
>> and and they didn't want to go around
arresting everybody who was actually
trying to make the system better because
they messed something up. And so the
Justice Department wrote a memo that
said, "We're not going to prosecute for
for this. And we're also not going to
prosecute if you just like violate the
terms of use, right,
>> of a system versus actually try to
breach it."
>> And and so I think the law is ample for
this for the scenario. And and it was
all written this GT Telemet was used by
NASA and Liverour and all the labs. And
so that's why it was it caught the
attention of DC because it was federal
systems that were being broken into. And
the problem we have now is is this is
this rift between the labs and the
security community that keeps looking at
all their postmortems and coming to two
conclusions. Sloppy
>> and and you're not complete in what
you're telling us happened.
>> And so of course the CBE process came
about in the 1980s. the the computer
virus and vulnerability reporting stuff
out of CMU and and for years they worked
on very structured reporting with
obligations and how to and there for
some reason they're not using any of
that to do this reporting
>> and so there is this very basic stuff
that I look at and say well until
they're doing that they really should
stop talking like they shouldn't
[clears throat] do a postmortem on a
breach
>> that looks like an intern wrote it and
it's not a postmortem it's this
selective memory it looks like
>> exactly the kind of postmortem you do
when you hire outside lawyers to
investigate some random thing and you
only give them certain stuff
>> because you don't have to give the
lawyers you hire all the information
about what happened
>> like where's all the Slack messages
where's the actual details of of what
happened can I can I just interject an
annoying aside so um which is which
is no no this is good which is very in
line with this which is um I've been in
the security like the actual cyber
security community for a long time and
it is you know it's always been one of
these things where like they just don't
like practical solutions. So even if you
build like you know a secure system like
well what if somebody you know shows up
like you know like
>> you know can Russell Crow can like break
the encryption [laughter] or something
like that.
>> It's Mission Impossible. Some
>> crew there's always like these kind of
like whatever. So my favorite thing that
happened recently was like Gnome Brown
some podcast we've all said stupid stuff
in podcast. I've already said
>> oh you didn't like this one.
>> NO IT WAS GREAT.
>> I THOUGHT IT was fun.
>> No it was fantastic. [laughter] No I'm
set I'm setting it up. Yeah.
>> So, so no Brown was like listen uh you
don't know what a super intelligence
could do. It could maybe use like the
heat of a uh CPU to excfiltrate itself
to another computer which this brought
me back to my
now I'm very comfortable right now I
could have endless pointless discussions
on this but what is interesting is you
basically have the X-risk people saying
something they thought was plausible and
then you have like the security people
having this kind of endless discussion
and so I think at some level
>> now these communities are being bridged
which is like you know I actually think
that was a very reasonable thing for non
brand to
I think you can pick holes in it, but we
all say weird stuff on podcast. I
actually think Xfill risk is real. I
mean, I worked in secure um computing
environments that were highly classified
that you would the covert channels were
unbelievable. you actually I mean so
these are very real comments but like we
actually have a real discourse and it
was the first time I saw really hardcore
systems people having pretty con like I
would say constructive
>> calculating the bit rate and
>> yeah it was great but it was a
constructive discussion and like you
know you had like the kind of the the
the typical extras people were engaging
of course it was it was Twitter so
there's like a lot of name calling this
and that but it was actually I felt like
a real discussion for the first time so
I hope we see more of this I hope we see
more
>> you know
>> you know cyber related things I think
the lab should talk more about it. I
think it'll engage the community and I
think once that happens, we can
>> actually Yeah, Greg's been out there a
lot more on this topic. Um, which has
been which has been good. But I think
the takeaway is Nam Brown should be
doing more brainstorms on podcasts.
>> I thought it was actually just it opened
people's eyes to the fact that actually
there's a lot of risks in security that
most people don't understand. Yeah. And
so that means that there's more stuff
that that like you can't make baseline
risk, you know, like how does your
authentication layer work? You can't
just wave your hand and say that should
go away and then bring up oh but you
know space aliens can invade and that's
a little bit of what was going on that I
felt uncomfortable with. But like what
what do you mean like it was sort of
like but you know there's also this risk
and is how I viewed that
>> of the heat thing. But but at least
we're now we're now in a in a domain
we're comfortable like I can talk about
entropy and like we can actually have a
concrete discussion that's not oh well
it's super powerful like at least we've
reduced it to like the laws of physics
and the laws of system. And and most
people did, I would say most people had
no idea that that kind of risk was real.
I mean, like when I'm walking around the
Persian missiles, I actually had to test
the graphics cards and PCs because a DoD
requirement is that the screen memory
not be sustained when you pulled the
power, but not for for zero time. Like
it the minute that the power went off,
the the memory image had to go. And if
there was like a 3se secondond delay,
>> Yeah.
>> Oh, you you you had that could be read.
Oh, see, see, we we had people that came
into our offices and would literally
measure the distance of the monitors to
each other because of Tempest attacks,
which is 100% a way to use
electromagnetic radiation to leak
information. I've seen the same thing
with spread spectrum from the BIOS. I've
seen it from I've seen it from from
audio speakers like we had to remove the
speakers out because it's a very high
channel.
>> Our building our building our building
had had just music speakers aimed at the
windows
>> just to produce interference.
>> You need to go run safety at one of
these labs. This is like I've never seen
you at more excited than heat, you know,
based communication.
>> Can I tell you the craziest covert
channel I've ever seen? So it turn
remember the old CR I know this is like
one of my
>> So I'm [snorts] glad that someone's
older than me. Not [laughter] really,
but acting it.
>> So remember the old CRT? So it turns out
if like let's say it's night and you're
you're using a CRT terminal in your
room, the lightest thing in the room is
actually the pixel that the raster beam
is on. So most people think it's like
the glow of the monitor, but it's
actually that given pixel. Mhm.
>> So, somebody figured out that like let's
say you're in like, you know, a hotel
room and you're on your computer. If you
have something that can sample the color
of the window, you can reconstruct the
screen.
>> Oh, that's crazy,
>> right? You just do it at the same hertz
that the raster beam is moving. Then
somebody else figured out if you can
subvert three pixels, you can use those,
you know, because it just looks like bad
pixels. You can use those to basically
send a message. So like you could
literally like sit out in whatever like
a you sample the message and you could
it was a relatively high bandwidth
oneway communication and so like what no
brown was saying like maybe heat is not
the way to do it but that level of
sophistication is actually real that's a
that's a thing
>> my I when I was at the missile factory
like I had to lock my keyboard up I
that's really an impolite word but
that's what we call something I had to
lock my keyboard up at night because
they didn't want the custodians who
didn't have clearance walking by and and
just noticing which keys were dirtier or
cleaner. And I once left it out and
there's like a a note from security,
>> you know, telling me to report to
security and pick up my keyboard.
>> Like the the guard who walked the
hallways just took the keyboard that
night off my machine. And that's like
basically I was not cleared. I was just
that sensitive, you know? I was like
nothing. I was an intern.
>> The big problem with this conversation
is now this is all in the training data
of every AI model in the future. So
>> but that's also but that's also the
threat model. Well, that but that's the
the the threat model for these things is
always you've got a trusted side and an
untrusted side. N has NIST has 500 page
manuals every
untrusted side you assume basically an
oracle that can do and know everything
and then the question is can you get
information off the trusted side which
by the way is what Nome was saying which
again is actually quite
>> which I do think brings up a super
interesting point which I'm going to
bridge to which is just that I think the
thing that people really aren't wrapping
their heads around and are using the
language that's really confusing is just
that what AI can do is it can try all of
those things in a very short time.
>> Yeah.
>> Yep. and and it doesn't get tired, it
doesn't get bored and you know and so
but the interesting thing about it is
there's a whole layer of security that
you now have to go look at every single
API, every single service you're running
internally on your network as like you
know like nobody thinks that their
internal GitHub or their internal Slack
or internal finance expense tool is is
vulnerable to a denial of service attack
but swarms
>> do it look literally look like a denial
of service attack.
>> Yeah. And so now we need a whole layer
internally that just is tracking way
more about what authentications are
being done, what APIs are being done.
Yeah.
>> And and but that's just like now it's
just going to be basic and and all the
offsite people that are old are like
mailing me like why are we explaining to
this to everybody? [laughter] It's so
basic because nobody did it internally.
>> Yeah.
>> And
>> well you didn't have to worry about it
for your people and that's the like
>> but now your person is just a piece of
software.
>> Yeah. And like unlimited and and the
>> has a credit card.
>> Yeah. I mean, we we you kind of got by
with with um information security like
to some extent uh on the fact that most
people will do the right thing 95 to 99%
of the time.
>> Oh, wait. Is that the malicious employee
is like one in 10,000?
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So, so like, so
all these systems are basically open to
whoever wants to access them or like one
tap on the shoulder and and then you
have access and agent swarms
>> completely flip that because they will
just these are just roaming you know
drones. Yes. And and but like yeah times
10,000 and and they will easily mistake
>> uh like a good task for a bad one and
and vice versa. So so the the data
security in our systems is a this is
going to be a huge upgrade moment. I I
actually Mart like I think that actually
we're going to need a different access
and security model. Yeah. Going forward.
Where are we going to go on that?
Because the model we have is not
granular enough and it's not performance
enough to handle this stuff.
>> So, so I want to step back. I want to
say like a meta like a meta point which
is I think this is how these
conversations should go. We've
identified a novel risk which is like
cyber security which we actually have
proof points and now we're talking about
solutions. I think the entire discourse
around AI can be of that form and that
the biggest mistake is that's not what
it's been like
>> I think the entire industry and
community is very happy to engage
exactly like this and I have something
to say about exactly what you're asking
but I say like like I think this is
where the conversation should be. So
>> we're known for having healthy
conversations that everyone should learn
from and so that's what we do.
[laughter]
So, so, so here's the thing. Um, I don't
think there's a a technical limitation
here. Like these threat models are very
well understood and have been in the
literature for a long time. I mean, like
the operating systems research, the um
MLS, the multi-layer security research
has has has considered these sorts of
things from an academic lens. The reason
it hasn't been adopted is just tended to
be a usability issue. Like, it's just
really hard to maintain and you didn't
have to. So you could argue that AI
solves the usability issue because it's
AI is using it. So maybe now is going to
be a renaissance in operating systems
and network and computer languages and
we should like go back to the old
research and we should kind of start
rebuilding systems that are secure by
design. And oh by the way if we don't
think that you know these things are
safe to put out we don't put them out
until we have these systems built and
and and oh by the way the AI is very
smart so they can help us build it. And
so I think again like computer owes a
like you know how much of the stack we
had to change for the internet.
>> Mhm.
>> Everything
>> right tell
>> and you you know [laughter]
you know how not vulnerable and how
vulnerable everything was like like we
could be in one of those moments like oh
we got to rethink everything and
that's fine. We've done that before but
but I think that's a conversation we
should have. So I agree it's time to
think about evolving these things.
>> Well like look at like here you
mentioned earlier like this booting a PC
and getting a virus in in 30 seconds or
whatever. So if you look at how like you
take an iPhone out of the box which a
lot of people are doing this week you
know the what happens is it the whole
network is basically shut down except
for getting the latest version of the
operating system because it doesn't even
though it's was pressed you know 6 weeks
ago
>> you know there some zero day thing has
been discovered since and so actually
the whole out of-box process now
involves first step update doing an
update where the the device can't do
anything else and it can never do
anything else until it's updated. That's
the like there all these benign things
completely benign
>> that we turned off in all of this
desktop software of the era that used to
be good things like it was having a
macro for words so you could build
automatic citations or something was
like this super cool thing until it
became a vir we had a thing where you
could put a CD in and it would just
arbitrarily run a program and so then
what somebody did was like oh well I'm
going to burn a clone of that CD and
replace the program with my virus but
it's going to look like the thing that's
supposed to run and it's just collecting
all stuff and being evil.
>> Yeah.
>> Then we disabled that. And so what one
of the things that's happening right now
is
>> we there's a whole bunch of stuff that
happens on like you on your own box corp
network
>> that actually is going to have to just
change as the the standard procedure.
Two factor off five years ago was not
standard in most places. the this whole
your whole like your whole SAS world
like I remember in like 2015 or so when
when you would talk to a new company
about their oh we're going to do
enterprise pricing and whatever and then
you they realized the first thing they
had to do was go do octa integration and
or Google off because they could not
have their own directory of of how to
manage it and then that just became a
thing and now there's not a SAS program
anywhere that doesn't just launch right
with managed authentication right
>> and and so there's just so many things
that need to happen before you you're
even software now.
>> Yeah. Well, yeah, we're we're uh I mean
there's probably every layer of the
stack has to evolve a bit on this. Like
even the like lack of granular nature of
like, you know, you have these modes of
like the agent will either ask you every
single time, you know, if it if you want
to, you know, give it permission to do
something or the exact opposite of like
it can just like delete your entire
computer, right? And like our OS
probably wasn't built for the right
level of of granular set of of tools you
want to give the agent. Um we we've kind
of done a lot of work work in this space
because obviously like you know do you
want to give an agent exact like your
entire file system? Probably not right
maybe in some cases you do but
oftentimes you want to have granular
controls of like in this folder you can
do read write and in that folder you can
only do read and and so how do you kind
of make this all intuitive for the user?
So it's it's very difficult and so so
there's going to like
>> Yeah.
What you just said [laughter] is a very
deep comment. I know exactly. Yeah.
>> Which is basically the conclusion of 40
years of
>> No% is like you actually can't
[laughter] make it. But maybe with AI
you actually can like maybe there is
like
if you ask me like walking in like what
I wrote down on my note like was my
biggest fear. Yeah.
>> Is that Europe decides that GDPR was the
best thing ever.
>> Uhhuh.
>> And they're going to just GDPR AI.
>> Yeah.
>> And and the AI will be fine. It'll be
have one it'll have one prompt for when
text gets emitted that just says this
vendor is emitting text and it's
probably wrong yes or no that that's
going to be because you can't really at
least in North America you're not going
to send your speech in Europe they still
will and and they'll have filters and
keywords and blog list but then on any
verb anytime that an agent or or you
know a background agent or a frontline
agent touches a third party product I
I'm really worried that they're just
going to say we need a GDPR prompt on
that and it's going to be
>> oh back to the user agent every single
write or every single nonlookup yeah
>> becomes like a a a safety warning like
the airbag thing in your car
>> and and the regulators love that because
it it's a liability assignment and so it
has this sort of legal precedent
>> and and I really worry that that's
that's actually the mid middle ground
where we're going to end up and and
unfortunately because the US about 15
years ago stopped leading in tech
antitrust. The the problem is that
Europe is going to lead with that
because they have nothing to lose.
>> Yeah.
>> Like there and and so I don't want to be
sad and down about it, but I I I just
can't get out of my head that they love
prompts.
>> They [laughter]
I mean, look, I had to put in that
browser choice thing. No, they they it
it because it it's the same. Look, get
into a new car. Yeah. which I haven't
done in years, but it, you know, like
you're pulling stickers off, you've got
you you know, you have all of these
things
>> and and someone thinks that that was
success. Yeah.
>> And it's like, has anybody ever read
like what is this if you're if there's a
baby in this seat? And it's like, well,
that's relevant for some people some of
the time, but it's this entire fabric.
[laughter]
>> It's attached to the seat and and they
love that that is a very particular
thing that they just love. And so I
would I would say if I were an AI now
the one thing I would be trying to avoid
and look we added it
>> okay FINRA for AI we'll we'll we'll
create that standard
>> I I mean look we had to put this we on
the on the when the internet was new the
big thing was to download a program and
run it and of course if your machine is
running in administrator mode it was
download a virus and take all your files
forever and so with with Windows um XP
which was in 2000 we added this thing
that prompted you and stopped like
literally your machine stopped user
account control and like it was absolute
assault and we also did it in Word the
stupid little macro to help you write
your thesis also came with a warning
every time you opened your thesis saying
this has my
>> everybody would just click
>> and everybody and so you you end up in
this world where just like with GDPR
everybody is numb
>> and so then they're like well it needs
to be bigger
>> although Mac I mean Mac kind of has
>> nobody downloads software that's the
thing it's a very different usage
pattern on Mac
>> so I I wish I
>> I don't have like I don't have like 10
applications on my Mac but Well, that's
but 10 and then you're done.
>> Yeah.
>> And it's But it's a lot of people
>> still do all this stuff. Imagine if
instead it was every time you go to a
new website.
>> Yes.
>> Which you do now because that would be
bad.
>> Yeah. I mean to to to start from here,
but to bring it kind of back to the the
macro like I wish this was the
discussion we were having which is like
>> I feel like we've dealt with a lot of
these problems. I feel like when we talk
about philosophical ex- risk, we're not
solving these very pragmatic problems. I
actually think this is actually a
constructive conversation to have. Maybe
props would help. I don't know. And I I
think part of the problem is is like
people don't remember like, you know,
how how unfettered access was and how
bad it was and just how relatively
benign that ended up being. Like I even
remember like there's at Stanford during
our PhD, I remember the oscilloscope was
kind of janky. I'm like, what's going on
with this oscilloscope? Like it's, you
know, it's a little slow. And I was
measuring the network traffic and it was
like more network traffic than you would
expect. Um, and I'm like, why is there
network? I didn't know the thing had a
TCP stack. somebody like broke in
because there's a old version of Windows
CE and was running a porn server,
[snorts] you know, and so like
>> I noted that
>> it it used to be
>> for the record nothing.
>> It it it used to be the case that like
anytime you turned over a stone
>> Yeah. Yeah. somebody had broke into
something and like was it this like
worstcase malicious whatever and as
actually very rarely even though the
capability was there and so if if we
could just some somehow tone down the
rhetoric and put it in context and these
still computer systems and yes there's
very serious stuff and people have
definitely died because networks have
gone down there's been real issues but
like and then can we just quibble about
GDPR that would be amazing but the
problem is like that's not the
discussion it's not about GDPR and
prompts it's about species extinction
and philosophy
>> and philosophy and and irrefutable
things and it's just
>> it's very soon like I I I think that
that's such a great point and I I think
you you hear people now talk about we
regulate airplanes and we regulate cars
and you forget like well the first cars
were at the turn of the century
>> and unsafe at any speed was in the mid1
1960s totally
>> and and you know people had been doing
selling pharmaceuticals in the during
the gold rush and theomide
you know, 50 or 75 years later and not
even in the US and then there was the
FDA and you know people the first pilots
were flying obviously at the beginning
of the 20th century and it wasn't until
the 1920s that you had to get a license
to be a pilot and you literally showed
up with your own plane and you got a
certificate [laughter] if you had it was
like getting it was literally no
different than driver's ed is today and
then it was 20 more years until they had
anything to do with airworthiness and
looking at your plane but it was it is
minimal. And then it wasn't until way
after World War I that they got involved
in like what you think of as the modern
FAA. And so you're looking at 40 years
Yeah.
>> of of innovation. And they were not
moving slow. I mean, if you ever seen
that video in black and white of like
all the different planes that crashed
and everything that was 20 years after
the Wright brothers
>> and is incredibly effective
>> and and and right, it's incredibly
>> it's the safest form of transportation
like you know and so I I do think that
this process
>> it's also the slowest most difficult
form of innovation. And so if you start
the F if you had started the FAA in
1910,
>> you never you never you never Well, I
was I was uh listening to a Nick
Bostonramm uh podcast just a couple days
ago. No, no, I I it was
>> it was interesting. It was interesting
and and but no, but but he actually
makes his point. If you regulate AI too
early, you actually basically don't
solve anything and you you you you still
just kind of had the same risk
ultimately, but you don't understand the
system. Then the you will the thing into
to to being but you haven't figured out
how to control it.
>> Well, we have to figure out what it
actually is. Yeah. Like like there are
new things coming out all the time and
like casting AI completely differently
as than we thought of just six or nine
months ago. And I think that that like
all the innovation that's going to
happen at the application layer is going
to cause things to move in and out of
the models in different ways. And like
we're we you know we we thought up until
last week I think that you know text
prompts and text coming back was going
to be the best way to interact with
>> I know then Jeff
>> and then Jeb Chef
>> so good too and then
>> so talk about that because I think
>> why you find it so remarkable. Yeah.
Well, okay. So, so the way I think about
it is um so okay, so LLMs were kind of
text in text out, right? They generate
text and and and they came from chat,
right? It was to communicate with a
human. And we've spent the last few
years trying to take this thing that
spits out text and cramm it into a
traditional program,
>> right? And but traditional programs
don't really speak text, right? And so
then you end up doing this janky thing
where you're like in the prompt you're
like
>> here's the schema,
>> here's the schema, but like the thing is
generating text and it kind of ignores
it and it's just been super janky. And
so what what Jeff basically said is that
listen um you know generating the text
on the is a very expensive thing but
it's also kind of you know it's more
complicated than you need. So why don't
we we we'll we'll we'll read text and
we'll have all of that kind of knowledge
to read the text but then rather than
generating text which is very expensive
we will just if you give us a set of
options we'll choose the best option. we
can do that incredibly um we can do it
incredibly fast, incredibly cheaply uh
but also we can do it with much more
accuracy because we can train just for
this. And so for all of the use cases
that are not talking to to like a a
chatbot but are actually trying to put
it in traditional software, this is a
great fit. And so this has probably been
the fastest adoption of an AI model
since chat GBT. It's just been
remarkable because we're all primed for
this. I just want to pile on this one
because I I can't tell you how much I
love seeing this exact form of of of
innovation and because what it does is
it does the thing that's bugged me from
the very beginning which is there's been
no user study ever that shows like
interacting with the computer using um
full natural language is efficient. M
>> it's it's like literally always the
least efficient way and it's very simple
and it's just like ask yourself how many
people are asked are really really good
at asking questions and immediately
that's like less than half the people
can ask a good question in a meeting.
>> Yeah.
>> And then how often do you look at the
answer and get really frustrated before
it's finished but you have to pay all
this money to watch the seven paragraphs
come out and then apologize that it's
only a little and so that's one like
having a different model. And then the
other of course is my favorite which is
the output of it is designed for
probabilistic programming.
>> Yeah.
>> And so instead of saying like is this a
customer service question then route to
customer service otherwise route to
general help desk or whatever it's like
well this is 80% customer service. And
that's exactly simulation. And it turns
out there's like 50 years of computer
science research in literally like
probabilistic if statements. And so
suddenly the coolest place to be in
computer science is going to be in
probabilistic programming which was like
all of computer science in the 1960s and
70s. So it was basically how do because
all of computers started with doing math
and it was all simulation.
>> So it was like let's launch the missile
and hit that target but it's windy
>> but wind isn't constant.
>> So like let's model the wind and decide
where to put the thrusters in order to
do the arc. And so most programming
through like say 1970 before it got to
accounting was probably
>> and then we ruined everything.
>> No, but accounting there's no
probability in accounting, right? But
but most programming was basically this
modeling kind of thing. And so most
programming language design was trying
to figure out how to put probability
into if statements or into while loops
like do this
>> until something happens maybe most of
the time. and and like so my first CS
class like the very second assignment or
so was a simulation about like waiting
online at a store and I didn't know it
at the time. I actually looked all this
up when I was reading about Jeb which
was like the the whole thing was my the
my professor was like wrote the book
called the theory of simulation in like
1960 and I just didn't know that because
it was kind of died by the 80s because
it was all replaced by hyper and so this
this notion of probabilistic
>> and and that slide deck you shared um
about the future what's different about
language models and stuff that you said
was super good. Oh, Halper Flags one
phenomenal Thomas great but the part
that I felt was missing was that like oh
wait this is not all new like like all
of computer science was this
probabilistic stuff and so it's going to
be very interesting
>> to dust off all of that work because
it's exactly what's going on like it's
not an if statement now is if x% not if
always and so the way that that Jev
worked is just to like you you basically
it's a custom programming language
almost which is here's the prompt come
back with a percentage. Yeah, that's
>> and then you put that in the if
statement. But the consequential thing
is like finally we have a way to
integrate these language models into a
traditional software and I think it's
kind of funny because it like you ask
the question like why haven't the labs
done this right and it's kind of like a
like not an indictment but a reflection
on how they think like they're trying to
create beings and beings speak if you're
trying to create god god speaks in
natural languages or whatever where this
is really about something that's for
traditional software which is kind of
not the direction that they've been
taken but one of the reasons the uptick
was been so dramatic is because a lot of
us software people have been trying to
integrate these models into software it
just hasn't so even before you get to
the probabilistic like if I want a
language model to drive an if statement
>> like it's really hard today with this
model it makes it much much much easier
and then of course this could change the
nature of software fundamentally to make
it more stoastic over
>> well I think but I absolutely and I
think that what's so cool is that that
it is happening outside the models
because that's what I think is just
going to happen which is the center of
innovation has just moved. Yeah. And
it's just and now people need to like it
turns out that the
>> I mean outside of the lab the big
>> the platform providers 100%
>> you know basically reach a critical a
point of critical mass where the
innovation stops happening at the
platform layer
>> and and then you know Apple there's this
famous expression in the Apple community
called sherlocking where Apple looks
around and the the things from the
outside world become features and people
complain and it's a real but that's sort
of how the innovation works because once
you're a platform you're overwhelmed no
matter how many people you add you're
overwhelmed with just keeping the thing
running and compatibility and stuff like
that. And so I think that this is the
signal that now people have figured out
that there's innovation to be done.
>> That's awesome.
>> To the model, but outside the model.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Guys, thanks for coming. This is great.
>> Okay, great.